Curriculum Vitae: Dominic Ken Muenzel

PhD Candidate; School of Biology; University of Leeds; LS2 9JT; UK E: bsdkm@leeds.ac.uk T: +44 7577 152452 ORCID: 0000-0002-7158-7748 SCOPUS: 57201616434

Personal Profile

My research investigates ways to improve spatial planning and conservation outcomes for tropical marine ecosystems by incorporating processes of ecological connectivity into decision making. I have previously worked on projects related to sustainable forestry management, international development, and marine fieldwork.

Work Experience

Oct 2017 - Jun 2018

Intern (6 mo) and Consultant (3 mo) at the German Federal Agency for International Cooperation (GIZ), Hanoi, Viet Nam

- Researching and reviewing the legal framework of forestry development, biodiversity conservation, payments for ecosystem services, and protected area management in Viet Nam under the programme "Conservation and sustainable use of biodiversity and forest ecosystem services"
- Supporting coordination of initiatives relating to illegal timber harvesting (FLEGT), forest degradation and loss (REDD+), and sustainable forestry certification (FSC)
- Supporting capacity development of government ministries and relevant institutions to meet national targets and international commitments such as the Convention on Biological Diversity and the Paris Agreement
- Presenting at meetings, workshops, and conferences on behalf of the programme

Jun 2016 - Aug 2016

Marine Research Officer at Frontier UK, Mafia Island Marine Park, Tanzania

- Oversaw the marine conservation programme through design and implementation of coral reef and mangrove surveys for Marine Park monitoring
- Trained volunteers in species identification and survey methodologies (e.g. underwater transect line) for benthic and pelagic communities
- Engaged and liaised with Marine Park staff and local community stakeholders in creation of the Marine Park management plan

Jun 2015 - Aug

2015

Research Assistant at HYDRA Institute for Marine Sciences, Elba, Italy

- Researched plastic biodegradability in the ocean under the EU-funded project "Open-Bio Elba Bio-Degradation of Bio-Plastics under Marine Conditions"
- Independently conducted related laboratory analyses
- Conducted scientific diving and sediment sample collection for partner universities

Jun 2014 - Aug 2014

Scuba Diving Instructor at École de Plongée Internationale de Calvi, Corsica, France

- Taught scuba diving courses and lead customers on exploration and try-dives
- Assisted with equipment maintenance, customer relations, and sales

Education

Oct 2018 current

PhD Managing tropical marine ecosystem interactions to improve the climate change futures of coral reefs, University of Leeds, UK

Sep 2016 – Sep 2017

MSc Ecosystem-based Management of Marine Systems, Distinction, University of St Andrews, UK

- Core Subjects: Ecosystem-based Approach, Marine Policy and Planning, Statistical Modelling, GIS for Environmental Management, Marine Research Methods
- Dissertation: Assessment of carbon emission reduction benefits in Scottish saltmarshes under different grazing regimes

2016

Dissertation: Inbreeding depression in parasite resistance of a free-living, Soay sheep island population

Curriculum Vitae: Dominic Ken Muenzel

Volunteering

May 2013 – Jul Coral Cay Conservation, Southern Leyte, Philippines

2013

- Conducted reef surveys on coral, benthic invertebrate, and fish assemblages
- Engaged in beach clean-ups and environmental education work with local communities

Sep 2013 – May

University of Edinburgh and Marine Conservation Society, UK

2014

Participated in restoration of natural parks and beach-clean ups around Scotland

Aug 2011

Klinikum Offenbach hospital, Germany

• Three weeks volunteering in patient care

Training Courses

Jul 2019	RangeShifter workshop in Bogor, Indonesia
May 2019	OpenNSPECT training online, hosted by NOAA

Feb 2017 Ecosystem modelling using Ecopath with Ecosim, Oban, UK

Awards

University of St Andrews - Dean's List for academic excellence 2016/2017

Skills

IT Skills MS Word, Excel, and PowerPoint (excellent), R (excellent), ArcGIS (excellent)

Research methods Population and ecosystem modelling, scuba- and boat-based surveying, literature reviews Languages German (native), Japanese (native), English (fluent), Italian (colloquial), French (colloquial)

Driving License UK Class B

Scuba Certificates CMAS 1* Instructor, FFESSM N4 to 60 meters, PADI Divemaster DSD Leader, PADI EANx 40%

Publications

Martino S. and Muenzel, D. 2018. The economic value of high nature value farming and the importance of the Common Agricultural Policy in sustaining income: The case study of the Natura 2000 Zarandul de Est (Romania). *Journal of Rural Studies*, 60, 176-187.

Muenzel D. and Martino, S. 2018. Assessing the feasibility of carbon payments and Payments for Ecosystem Services to reduce livestock grazing pressure on saltmarshes. *Journal of Environmental Management*, 225, 46-61.

Country Experience

Work	Viet Nam, Tanzania, Italy, France, Philippines, Germany
Living	UK, Italy, Germany, Ivory Coast, Viet Nam, Tanzania

References

Dr Maria Beger, Academic Fellow, University of Leeds, m.beger@leeds.ac.uk

Dr. Simone Martino, Postdoctoral Research Associate, University of York, UK, simone.martino@york.ac.uk